many of the practices that I take taught
people like the meditation contemplation
Tai Chi Chuan they can be pursued in a
very individualistic fashion and that's
always concerned me and I would it's
important to bring back a community a
dialogic aspect to people's attempts to
respond to the mean Christmas I think
this is really I was gonna say integral
but that's probably bad Association
historically but it's really integral to
to the kind of response I think people
need right right totally so that's why
it's important to me yeah yeah I have to
say that here's the thing I just want to
say it just kind of start off start off
by saying which we touched on before one
it's wait so I just I just hit the
record button so those those of you who
are listening we got right out we got
right into it and it was like we
couldn't you know we just there's so
much we both wanted to share with one
another yeah and a lot of it has been
what's just there for me is I just have
just actually deeply appreciated one the
scope of your work but also it's
strangelet strangely enough this huge
scope of your work that includes
literally almost everything right yet
this felt sense that I've always had in
and every time I've seen you talk every
video I've I've I've seen every
interview that I've seen of you how
deeply personal it is at the same time
yeah very much things have used to me
has been part of part of what's really
had me watch all of your interviews and
if that just seems very very present for
me um thank you I I think that's a very
acute observation because that is that
is very much an explicit goal especially
for something like the series but even
in my academic teaching I try
as much as possible to do that right to
try and give people both simultaneously
a broad scope but you know a very sort
of present access to it so that they're
there they're being existentially
confronted not just nearly informed so
that there's an idea here note there's
there there there's there's a potential
way of thinking being that on offer here
as well and and that should challenge
you it's it's a challenge I mean my hero
is Socrates right and and so that that
very much of that sense of that I'm not
just I'm not just teaching in a sense of
giving information I'm trying to
challenge people to confront them in a
way that allows them to potentially
starting engaging in self-reflection
waking up its in some way and so that's
that's very very important and and and
and like Socrates there's a self
reflective aspect of that so when I'm
when I'm teaching others that's also a
process of Socratic self-examination for
me
I'm involving myself in the process I
very much see teaching as sharing of
learning rather than the dissemination
of information yeah existentially
challenged yes right that's it that that
word struck me yeah I'm trying to convey
with that the that there's a sense that
a deep education is an aspirational
project in there in the sense that Agnes
color talks in her book aspiration that
we're trying to become someone else and
this is a very odd thing for us to do
because we and you know at La Paul talks
about this in transforming expect we
don't know we don't have those sets of
preferences we don't have those values
and in language we were talking about
earlier we don't have that world yet we
haven't moved into that world and so and
how do we get there and how do we how do
we how do we how do we need people into
the aspirational project of trying to
become you know more more more virtuous
more wise more more connected more
capable of meaningful connections to
themselves and to others and these are
all these are all deeply aspirational
things and it until you have to confront
people right that they it's like the
Socratic aporia you have to get people
to they have to be willing and in this
and I mean it's an existential sense
before they can go on an aspirational
quest they have to be able to
fundamentally question how they're
framing themselves and their world and
to be they have to be able to put into
question their identity and the way
they're identifying things and oh and
say wait wait there are real the world
and the way the world and I in a
co-creating fashion we make it they can
be fundamentally other than they are and
perhaps better well so there's a what
I'm what I'm what I'm hearing and that
is uh that for you
it is really personal yes it is very
personal in such a way that everything
right it's it's it's that you want do
you want people to be confronted right
and you made this may this distinction
because in some sense what we're wanting
is to become what we aren't yet yes and
that that that is that happens through
being confronted with that tension
mm-hmm between the two and so what I'm
hearing you say is one of the ways that
you offer that confrontation is by being
confronted yourself yes in your teaching
yes very much so it's it's like you
almost have to become a symbol in the
ancient meaning of the word like you
have to be somebody that can enter the
like can enter the world of the student
as they are but can also like I don't
know what the word is like tempt them
like or open up them to that this other
world as a viable possibility to them
and so
you you you yeah you you that's it that
that is deeply messed with the kind of
self knowing in which you yourself are
also in this reflective reflexive
process of transformation and change
very much very much Wow I it's
interesting I just feel in the in the
presence of that right now
right which is often often seems to be
the case with you with your work is it
there is this element of like you're not
just intimidating information that
you've already worked out no it seems
like you are on the precipice of
something right like that even if you've
already known it the way that you're
saying it feels very alive and so so so
often what I find in listening to your
lectures is this experience of where I'm
like at the precipice of thinking with
you right good good that's exactly what
I want that's exactly what I want that's
exactly what I want yeah I mean even
when I sort of have a prepared point or
direction I'm very much trying to get
into the flow state so that I talked
about I'm always trying to do it as jazz
that right that that there's all that
I'm open to the flow of what's happening
and improvisation and insight so that
the argument and the material and in the
world of the person I'm talking about
have a chance to impact on me and speak
through me and and generate an insight
in me and then though the best lectures
for me are exactly the ones in which
that occurs in which oh let's say I'm
talking about Plato and as I'm doing it
I suddenly see something in Plato I
haven't seen before and then I can
articulate that at that moment with
people that that that that's exactly the
best teacher that's huh
when you say best well cut a couple
things what what really struck me we
said yes that you do that's exactly what
I'm going for
what's it like I mean what's it like
just to hear that like it's good thank
you because that recognition it's
helpful it it makes me sense it gives me
a sense that yeah it's working in some
fashion yeah so there's a there's a way
in which where where when you said it
gives me a sense right that's some I
would imagine that sense I get this
sense of like yeah I'm already feeling
for what I'm doing so there's a sense
that I'm that I'm I'm doing the lectures
right I'm doing these interviews I'm on
this I'm on this interview right now I'm
in this conversation right there's all
the particular things that I'm doing but
there's a background sense that I'm I'm
taking on which I imagine for you what I
kind of imagine with you that's kind of
a 24-hour job this sensing right yeah
that's just in the sense that I get I
just get the sense of a total sense of
devotion to what you're up to right
that's very much true yes there's a
sense there's a sense of devotion and
there's there's very much a sense a
sense of it's just it's not the right
word I was gonna say reaching but
reaching isn't the right word because we
Qing implies that you're not in contact
with it but there's a sense of grow of
moving beyond that that I'm always right
there that there's this there's a more
Ness that comes in and it enriches what
I'm doing and I'm constantly listening
for that more ness and I'm constantly in
love with it and constantly sensitizing
myself to it if that's what you mean
yes yes for me listening for that more
Ness that's just great way of putting
that listening for that more Ness
that I really relate to that in so many
ways because I would say that in the
practice of circling I we could very
much say is that we're all gonna sit and
get really present and listen for that
more Ness yeah yeah yeah I mean that's
what I experienced when I did the
circling that's why I found it so
profound because it resonated it was it
had an affinity with what you and I are
talking about now an affinity with that
I so I it was new right but it was also
it's to some degree recognizable to me I
went it was like oh yes yeah now would
you say see to me
I've we talked about this a little bit
earlier before before I hit the record
button
but that listening to that more Ness
mm-hmm and your your work as a
philosopher and when you're doing
philosophy is that a lot of what
philosophy is for you yeah I mean that's
I mean it depends there's two different
I I often rely on a distinction between
the word philosophy
I value both of these first of all but
distinction between philosophy and
philosophy
Safiya philosophy is this professional
enterprise that's part of my job my
vocation and I really I really enjoy its
learning right how to you know
critically reflect upon argumentation
theories ontological all that stuff
right that right but then there's this
other thing which is and I use the word
philosophy and I'm harkening back to PR
those idea of philosophy as a way of
life and what if his books was entitled
that right and how those the hope that
that the ancient tradition that what
we're trying to do is cultivate a love
of wisdom and that's another way of
talking about this this sensitizing
myself right listening for the morning
trying to get caught up in it as it
flows and that's definitely the
philosophy that I'm practicing and part
of part of my challenge is to get those
two
talking really well to each other so
that they're they're actually informing
each other did that seems to presuppose
that they're often not are they
sometimes yeah so very often world I
mean well in the world and also in my
own personal history I mean I went into
university I had already sort of
encountered the meeting crisis in
literature I'd read I'd read some really
important science fiction book that sort
of opened me up I was in within a
Christian upbringing and it opened me up
to Hinduism and Buddhism and then I read
you know sit hearta by Hermann Hesse and
I start reading a young and and so has
already opened up and I went into
University and I read Plato and I
encountered what I would call philosophy
yeah right and the figure of Socrates
and I touched on this and are right and
but as I pursued that the pursuit of
wisdom right but falls off the table in
academic philosophy at that time and
then it became this other thing his
reflection on science reflection on
culture and I found that independently
valuable but the need that was being
Matt when I had encountered Plato and
Socrates was not being met anymore by
philosophy so I felt those two diverged
and that's why I went it and started
doing Taichi and learning the pasta and
meta because that's where I was that was
where I was able to again get into that
you know that philosophy uh-hmm it's
only recently that and fortuitously for
me that those two streams have come back
together so that people within academic
philosophy and academic psychology are
now seriously talking about things like
wisdom and transformative experience and
mystical experience right Wow okay so
invent in it so so that there was a way
in which in your earlier in your earlier
years before before college that you
were already reading some of the things
that actually like wake people up a lot
right yes very much very much and then
you got you got into when you went into
school mmm
you started pursuing knowledge and then
you got morale of the of the part that
like doesn't include the experience of
knowing mmm la Sofia yeah yeah and so
then you went then you went off and
started to do Tai Chi what were some of
the other things that you did IVA
Pastner which is a terribie inform of
mindfulness meditation and Metta which
is a contemplative practice and what was
fortunate for me and this was the
original inspiration for some of the
work I do on the idea of an ecology of
practices I was taught all three in an
integrated fashion the Tai Chi and the
past of meditation and the meta
contemplation were taught as mutually
informing constraining and affording
each other Wow and and when you were
doing that while you were studying
philosophy they happened at the same
time right yeah did you know were you
aware at the time between the connection
between the two I was aware of a hunger
for the connection between the two and
and and and there was a very dim sense
of not knowing what I was looking for so
the problem was I kept reading you know
and I would read Nietzsche and I read
lots of Heidegger two courses on how to
there and reading all this and and and
what and it was it always slowly dawned
on me that what I wasn't getting right
from the philosophers I was getting a
lot I was getting tremendous out of
Nietzsche and Heidegger and people like
that but what I wasn't getting I wasn't
getting an ecology of practices and it
wasn't getting what I was getting with
the Tai Chi and the capacitor meta I
wasn't getting yes you're telling me
that I need to go through this
transformation I can't know this without
being transformed but you're not
actually telling me how to transform
you're just telling me transform
transform but yes but how how do I
transform what's that's like and and
it's not just getting a skill he's kind
of these are transformations of your
identity your being in the world like
this this is a radically challenging
thing so it's not just how do I do it
like learning a skill is like well we're
like how what is it to go through this
kind of
transcendence this kind of self
transformation you know that needs a
kind of deep guidance and like I said it
wasn't finding yet whereas when I when I
read ancient philosophy like in reading
Plato and you're reading the dialogue
you're getting it's exemplified it's not
just talked about
yeah it's exemplified or you were you're
meeting Marcus Aurelius in reading the
meditations he's not just making claims
he's also taking you through spiritual
exercises that are transforming your
consciousness and cognition or your
reading plus - like one of my favorites
you're simultaneously going through an
argument and you're going through this
it's almost like a guided meditation
where he's taking you through this
radical transformation of your car
consciousness and cognition and I'm
seeing and I and I want that and wasn't
getting that is it fair to say you
wanted to be existentially confronted
yes yes very much very much very much
and there was something about the way
that that was being explored in college
wasn't wasn't providing that you're both
you're both mostly just getting the
instructions - without how yes yeah very
much enemy and there was even like I
said there's even an absence of the
discussion of wisdom you know there was
lots of discussion about morality not
very much about meaning except if you
took a course on existentialism right
and and and the topic of wisdom I mean
it's ironic in this discipline by law
finally as Sophia that has wisdom in its
name that wisdom was not a topic of
discussion and so I felt that I felt
both that the the explicit foregrounding
of the topic and the pursuit was being
neglected and then as you mentioned I
was not being I was not I want to use
the word guided as opposed to just
instructed I wasn't being guided I
wasn't being led into a path which is
what I was looking for right and so you
were as you were I'm getting this in so
as you as you were learning write it in
college
you're also what what were you getting
out of consciously at the time like what
were you
doing when you were doing the Taichi and
well those things they talked about like
what at the time what were you doing it
and why were you doing it what were you
getting out of it like what was it what
did you call it back then so I mean I
did think of it pretty much as the
cultivation of wisdom as distinct from
knowledge I started to making a
distinction between knowledge which is
like what you know and wisdom which is
how you know and and that was already in
my mind as a distinction so I I have
started to frame it that way but what I
was getting out of Tai Chi was this
sounds I don't mean to sound trivial but
it didn't but it's really it was really
important like you I was getting regular
access to the flow experience and and
that was that was like that was very
very powerful to me and then I started
to get and the flow experiences I mean
the flow experience take I mean one of
its features is it takes you out of it
you know an egocentric narrative frame
of mine and it gives you this radical
sense of at one mint and connectedness
and it really and it's and it's a it's
your optimally performing and it's
optimally motivating so it very much is
a very it tempts you into transformation
in a any very powerful way so I was
getting that from the the past 'no i I
was getting that you know that sense of
self-awareness like I often use the
metaphor you become a connoisseur of
your own experience your the ability to
taste and deeply from stance you know an
experience and and that was starting to
make me aware and it was starting to
link up to the work I was doing in
psychology so they were starting to talk
to each other where of the prevalence of
you know self-deceptive ways of thinking
and being and being able to not just
know about them and believe about them
but to use a link or term we've been
using confront them yeah yeah and as an
existential challenge to be addressed
that was one of the primary things the
meditation was doing and what was
interesting is how one of the like I
didn't even notice some of the change
I remember one of my good friends Dan
Shafi somebody I do work with now and
other people they they came and said to
me at one point is it what what's what's
going on I said what do you mean I
thought I'd done something wrong and
they said you're right in the way you
write and the way you talk and it's
different now that it used to be your
doing those things differently I hadn't
even realized that it had permeated into
my way of thinking and talking and only
when somebody had pointed it out to me
do it I realized ah now I see now I see
did you think is i i i was really
getting a clearer sight you can almost
feel kind of Hegel in the backdrop here
it's like this the sense of getting you
could say be its philosophy a-- uh in
terms of your experience of wisdom and
then what was the other one that you
call it the other part philosophy
philosophy right and as we were talking
about I got this really clear sense of
being in a dialectic between one and the
other yeah then you said before you knew
it before you you didn't recognize it
until somebody pointed it out yeah very
much about that seems important been
that it happened before you recognized
it without you quite knowing what's
important about that what's important
about that is is it's again it was
consonant with this realization of
overcoming self-deception if I was just
saying to myself ah look at John look at
look at there's a sense in which I was
suspicious about about the fact that
this had permeated up outside of that
ego narrative direction and had been
recognized independently in a convergent
manner by other people from the outside
that gave it a kind of legitimacy that
made it very very telling for me okay
cuz it's like okay so I just want to
make sure that I get it is like that
that could dot like they that the
dialectic started to synthesize if you
sent if T if you will sure and it was
already happening and then someone else
recognized it there was something about
that that like no one that that one it's
happening it's happening at below
level of like conscious recognition yes
very much
because if it wasn't conscious
recognition you you could you could you
could still kind of yourself
couldn't you yes very much
it to happen and then just cut
interpreted but that somebody caught you
at it in a certain sense yes recognize
it is true something about the I get the
sense of like a bottom-up experience
very much that's it that's exactly the
right way of putting it yes yes so just
that experience of just curious if we
just kind of hang with that for a moment
just that experience of these two worlds
coming together in the way that they did
it's funny I that I I'm I'm now going
back through all the work that I've seen
you do right did I've experienced and it
occurs like a fractal of that yeah yeah
for you yeah I mean that's kind of a
window I mean when those two it's like a
triangulation when those two aspects
talk to each other and I get a sense of
recognition from others that's when I
that's like this triangulation on the
more nests that I was taught that's what
really that's what I get a sense that
I'm I often say I feel like I'm on the
track of the truth when I'm doing when
that when those line up in that way yes
you're under the track of the truth and
that experience so one of the things I
really I was curious about I wanted to
ask you about was your work on the
meaning crisis I think there's things I
think that um the edits that you named
it right and that you're putting it
central in what you're doing is so
timely and it just feels right on right
and I'm hearing other people to refer to
it ya know if you came up with it with
the term yeah I did I mean other people
have talked about crisis of meaning but
I put I put it together as a meaning
crisis and then as a term and then and
get with working again with Christopher
and with Phillip right and other people
Leonardo and Anderson I like I want
people understand it
there's many people involved in this but
yet being able to put a name to it but
also a history to it because the two
have to go together right name without a
history isn't really a name it's just a
label right so but putting a name with
the history to it
that was that was sort of the aha I
think that name in the history do you
remember do you remember was there like
a moment where that yeah helped him when
I was teaching the course so I so a good
colleague a friend of mine Evan Thompson
was supposed to teach a course called
Buddhism and cawed side Buddhism in
cognitive science and he couldn't do it
and he said a John would be a good
person to do that and I started doing
this and I was interested in wiser this
grow I just it struck me as this
question why is there this growing
confluence between Buddhism in coxide
why are they talking to each other what
and you could see why I'd appealed to me
here's Buddhism here's a practice as the
philosophy and here's cognitive science
doing all the theory and now they're
talking to each other so of course this
was personally very interesting to me
and I'm picking this up and I'm trying
to get this and I'm thinking oh there's
an issue about meaning and connectedness
and then I and as I was teaching and
trying to lay out why they're coming
together it hit me and then I felt like
oh wait there's a history here there's a
history of how we got to this place
where this confluence makes so much
sense and I'm like it happened when I
would like one of the first time I was
lecturing and as that course involved
like I used the course I don't mean an
exploited in fashion right I used the
course right to develop this argument in
concert with students and that's how it
came about yes in concert with students
yes and do you remember like that so do
you remember there was a moment where it
came together were you like in front of
the students or was it as you're
thinking about doing the class it was
there a moment or was it a gradual
within an hour ten days so so both I
mean there were moments where things
came together and the proverbial penny
dropping and and I would just see that
right like there was a moment where I
saw oh they're coming together because
there's a crisis of meaning there's a
meaning
yes right yeah and then and and there
was it there was sort of a a sense of
the history and there was a sense of
sort of two aspects here a personal and
a historical and trying to get those
really and that was all there but then
the the sort of putting together of the
argument I couldn't have that developed
as I was teaching the course as I you
know as I was reading so many excellent
books on mark Taylor's book after God
had a huge impact on me and then and
then what happened what happens it's
like that like you know what Tillich
calls a Kairos as I started reading one
of these books it let it just it was so
fruitful was like something growing
organically one book would lead to
another and they were just so mutually
facility and and as I was learning as I
said I would be sharing that learning
with my students when they work the fact
it was because of my students that I did
this series yeah I had done that I'd
done it and then I so he said you should
record it and I record it and then one
of my students had taken Buddhism in
Clarke's lie with me and he said you
know the the version you have on YouTube
it's like you know the production
qualities are horrible the sound is bad
and you know like let's do a really
really good version of this and so they
because and so the fact again that again
you see somebody from the outside came
to me and said we want to take this out
into the world that's what that's what
I'd happened and they came in from from
the outside um but in the context of
having of listening to you
yes yeah very much very much there's
there's something that just kind of um I
want to I want to tease out here a
little bit with you so it's oh sure
so I'm imagining this could have
happened when you were reading a book by
yourself on a retreat is gonna not a
number of different places but it did
but it happened with others and
precisely in another's listening yeah um
that there's something about I'm
wondering about this cuz it because I I
think why does one of the reasons this
this stands out for me is that having
been innocent
some version of a similar position is
you in with with circling being a
teacher teaching people how to circle
right and having these year-long courses
that I've been inside of one of the
things I've noticed is I'm I I'm in some
level I feel grown up by the listening
of my students mm-hmm yes many things
that have turned out to be the things
that weren't there that are now most
important to me in my life that are
there I were brought up by my students
were influenced because the hunger for
learning in the things that they want to
learn - had me go to a deeper place in
myself yes that in sentiment so many
ways I feel I face has been shaped in
the last 20 years literally Hey the
listening of my students in that that
rich conversation and I sometimes wonder
about like I wonder where I'd be if I
had never started teaching I just wonder
what I would be interested in like if if
some of the thoughts that I've had the
insights yeah I I can't I can't I can't
do it without others that I mean III
very what I mean if I can't do the what
kind of work I love doing even when I'm
writing I almost always writing with
somebody else
III deep I mean I deeply believe in that
platonic thing that together in dialog
were capable of something we can't reach
on our own and that lines up with
psychology it lines up with Vygotsky and
other things right and and so yeah very
much students they challenge you and
they literally encourage you in ways
that you can't do for yourself and and
that's I mean I that's one of the
reasons I love teaching and I also love
that I can see that that happens for
them there's a recipients reciprocal
like when they open me up it generally
is consonant with them opening up and
then and then they're there is that kind
of mutually accelerating disclosure kind
of thing right there's there's five
which is a kind of love right it's the
love right of communitas of people
working in concert together it's finally
finally is that that that that love I'm
feeling right now with you yes that's
exactly right yes and for me I finally
is really important because finally uh
finally uh it's is the transformative
bridge between Eros and agape I think
you get you get two you get from arrows
to agape raya Pylea I hate oh
interesting okay so there's a yes so
arrows meaning and if I remember right
is like it's a love that wants to eat
you don't want to be one with yeah and
that can be even mystical oneness it
doesn't have to be just sexual but it's
it's yeah it's a it's it's let's be one
let's be one right yeah both recommend
deeply consuming God and being consumed
by God yes yeah that's fine yes and then
there's a my dear yes well I just want
to go to the other one that a bridges
agape yes which is how would you how
would you put so if if if eros is that
consumed Ettore my tenth and I think of
agape as creative it's it's right so I
love because my love is creating meaning
and a meaning maker not because I'm
getting something from them it's so the
prototypical instance is and it's the
biblical example right is the love a
parent has for a newborn child you you
don't love the child of erotic lee
that's deeply wrong they can't the child
can't enter into folia with you they do
not have the capacity you don't love
them for those reasons you love them
precisely because but by loving them you
get to participate in the create the
creation of God right right I don't mean
God being created God's creation of
people if you'll allow me to speak
mythologically right and so I mean
that's how the New Testament sees it I'm
not a Christian I'm not advocating for
Christianity but that's that they are
right then that literature is the
prototypical literature I think to turn
to and you want to understand
right so you're you're you're turning
your you're turning a non-person in some
sense I don't mean mortal either
non-people but you're turning a non
person into a person it is it is it is
it is the deepest kind of creativity
that a human being can participate in
and it is it you're not you're
transcending just making meaning there's
there's something more to it you're
actually participating in them a meaning
making that makes meaning makers mm-hmm
you're participating in a meaning making
that makes meaning makers yes Wow
there's something so what it takes I'm
noticing what it takes to understand
that is it's an experience of it it's
interesting a meaning making that makes
meaning makers huh I just noticed thing
as I'm understanding that I'm I'm
mapping it I'm noticing it bringing back
experiences of the past and with this
frame I could see it through that frame
of what it was like raising my son yeah
what's it like being with students what
it's like where I've been on the side of
that and you're right oftentimes as an
adult it does seem like that that in the
middle one that you talked about
philosophy a-- yeah valia valia idly yes
by Leah really fly Leah really that's
why it's the it's I'm struggling for the
right word here but it's it's the
platform it's the affordance right why
Leah gets you into the kind of
relationship with meaning making and
mutual disclosure and be president
allows you to be unselfish Ave becomes a
real possibility for you right so that
that particular entry into knowing right
where and it sounds very similar is is
it similar
- you're the dialectic that was
happening for you just in your life we
go back between when you entered into
the more of the philosophy like the
philosophy ax or Lhasa fee that it is it
something about what was that it does
that fit in there between what we're
talking about now it I get the sense of
that on one side there's the knowledge
right to concretize right that you're
learning cool now on this side is almost
like that the knowing without
necessarily the knowledge yeah and
that's what I mean when I think what I
said where wisdom is about the how and
that's why I you know what I'm talking
about wisdom and meaning making I talk
about the four ways of knowing rather
than the four kinds of knowledge because
I'm trying to talk about a process that
you're involved in and I'm trying to get
back to the ancient idea which I think
we need to recover that there are
aspects of our self knowledge other than
our autobiographical right there's
aspects of self-knowledge and of knowing
others and knowing the world that can
only be known within a process of
transformation we can't we can't just
know them as the grasping of cross
proposition we can only know them
insofar as we are coupled to them and
being transformed in connection to them
right
Rikka ease the word recover yeah which
is interesting is this it's interesting
that connotes two things yeah
if kind of it's like the the unveiling
yeah and the veiling in would you say if
I recover do you mean something like I
want to reveal mmm-hmm the the how
recover the how of it and what and
currently the how is covered so I'm I
want to I want to unveil the how and
then recover the dogma of it yeah a
little bit or I would hasten ship there
is there I was thinking more I haven't
thought about recovering the dogma
because there is a sense which I'm
trying to break the fixation on the the
you know the assertion of propositions
but I was also yeah well you're talking
about this earlier the sense of like
like they're in in that process of
transformation right there's also you
know there's and I was just reading out
some abstains book on pseudo dynein like
there's there's a terrific element of
Unknowing you have to there's a that you
have to go through right there's a sense
in which you you have to confront you
have to you have to confront the fact
that to you some of my language you know
that the framing is never in the frame
the process by which things are being
framed never comes up as something
within the within your frame right it's
always it's always something you you can
you can only know it by being it you can
never have it as a focal object of
awareness so there is a kind of being
able to accept that phenomenological
mystery I'm not saying it's a
theoretical and explicable 'ti I can
talk to you about it but there's a sense
in which it's like there's a
phenomenological mystery to my own
framing right that it's it's always only
something that I know through it's never
something I know yeah as an object right
and that there's something yes the
background can't ever be you can ever
see the background there's another way
of saying that you can never see the
background in the foreground as the
background in the moment yeah exactly
exactly yeah yeah you know you you you
the I can't see it's up we have lots of
metaphors for this you can't jump over
your own shadow although all those kinds
of things yeah very much right and in a
certain sense it sounds like a bit of
when those two philosophy and falafels
La Sofia came together it sounds like
that that was probably a moment where
those two were the background right and
the foreground kind of came together and
peaked their heads from one another a
bit yeah there is there is that yeah
that's very good I hadn't put that
clearly in my mind the way you just did
but you're right though there was
there's a kind of mutually accelerating
disclosure going on that way that's
resonating with the mutually
accelerating disclosure that's going on
between me and the world or between me
and other other people my students I
hadn't thought of that but I think
that's very hopped yes except they think
one of the things one is i i i feel
appreciative of your openness to be
influenced by something that the
questioning and the conversation just
like just the sense of that just the
sense of like oh I've never quite
thought about it like that
I felt I just felt a sense of like just
being in participation with what yeah
that's that's important to me
me so again all evoke a platonic
distinction I mean Plato makes a
distinction between philosophy and Philo
nykeya which is the love of victory and
and and so you see a lot of discourse
today is is built on the law of a
victory about right about you know
demolishing and destroying and debunking
and you know and it's and and I'm
philosophically deeply opposed to this
precisely because and Plato represents
this is one of the most pervasive kinds
of ways in which we can
ourselves thinking we're doing
philosophy when we're actually doing
exactly the opposite because we're
pursuing we're actually caring about
victory we're not caring about truth or
learning and so it's very important
right to me to embody that that I should
be learning if we're in genuine dialogue
with you I should be learning from you
right but right it should be or or I'm
not I'm not in dialogue with you I'm
just trying to get my point across
etc and I think one of the reasons I'm
so interested in you know in this whole
authentic discourse movement and
circling is precisely to shift off of
violet pride Leah
Nakia right and back onto finally Oh
Sophia yeah this court with discourse
that's what that's why like that's why I
and like so that people people will
regularly have these kinds of things
like you just said where like like oh
right yeah
John is learning from me right and and
and yeah exactly right this is so it's
like a like it isn't it fair to say
it's a fair to say having a the kind of
listening that that opens to novelty in
a what in such a way that creates
stability yeah that's what I means by
the Jazz of it like getting into it like
the Jazz of it because you jazz isn't to
be to do kharkov honest knows you're
still what you do is like it's you know
it's self-organizing criticality you
push the form so that it breaks and
opens to novelty but you don't push it
so it destroys you what you're doing is
affording it to be able to reconfigure
itself again and again and again
that's exactly so you see the there back
and forth of the Platonic debate as
doing that rather than one side trying
to crush the other side down yes yes
so there's I'm getting a sense of this
this I'm also getting this sense of
justice dialectic in a way or the
synthesis that it sounds like it's very
much through your teaching and through
your life and is even happening right
now yeah very much that's what I'm
feeling right just that just that sense
of your awareness to to I think what how
we often call it encircling how I often
see it is that which is most alive and
is like that which is most alive is like
life has this way we're kind of one of
the things that seems like it makes life
life is it as this way of opening to the
to the novelty of the environment in
such a way that it's openness allows it
to persist your instability that that
that is so prescient I mean the most
recent episode of the series and I was
coming on this idea that the core of
cognition is this process I call
relevance realization and the main
metaphor I use for that is it's like the
analogy is the way life has evolved like
like what the right happens is it opens
itself up to variation and then puts
selective pressure back down and then
from that we configuration it Rivera's
itself and then it reconfigures itself
like it's through selective pressure and
so it's constantly
right it's constantly about and that's
what I see your relevance realization
machinery is doing
you're constantly evolving your sensory
motor fitted miss in moment by moment to
to the environment to the situation
that's how you're in it you're
constantly evolving your constraint on
the problem space so that you constantly
are refitting yourself again and again
and again moment by moment to the
situation and would you say thank you I
I love how it's all like I'm looking
forward to listening to our conversation
feeling the the movement of the dialogue
because it's it does seem like it's
what's happening for me much very much
for me to that mutual space of an
openness to things that have my life
make more sense to me yeah like it's
it's and everybody's hungry for it well
sorry that's that's selection bias on my
part the people that I meet in my work
and who come to me because of the series
come to me precisely because there is
this hunger for this this right and we
use we use this word meaning it's a
metaphor you know we're something like
what a sentence has but again it's this
it's this evolving connected like you
said it's opening us up but constantly
connecting us together and there's a
sense again
well while I'd say like there's maybe
this is what you mean by the aliveness
for me years there's a sense of the
morning there's something more than you
and I like coming in and through this
and taking us somewhere yes yes in that
when you said the people that you're
meeting
there's openness to or a hunger for this
yes yeah i i'm just cure it just gotta
be a trip being you right now is kind of
like well invite you to be tripped out
about it if you if you aren't already
but just the sense of that you know that
white on some level even pre
reflectively on
you've been interested in this sweet
spot right yeah
spot of what we're calling the more
nests or the yeah the aliveness yeah
this mutual sale self-transforming
openness right yes leads to a greater
stability to do more of that right
that's very much yeah that that even
just right now and also in your life you
are you have people that want you want
you to share that with them yes in in a
way that you're you're actually in the
process itself yes your life is just
about that um so in that sense it's a
trip that I get to live out my Socratic
dream if that's not too pretentious that
that's yeah in that sense I have good I
mean living Socratic dream that's not
that sounds like something I just wanted
to highlight that an extreme that's
beautiful yeah thank you
i I mean it's challenging for me that's
why I was hesitant
I mean I'm by nature very socially
phobic and so doing this even doing the
series and and that's why when I went to
the circling and Peter suggested me
Peter Lindbergh suggested that I be
somebody that they they do the the
birthday event every five mi being said
no which is precisely why I did it
yeah right because that's the Socratic
courage right and if I didn't have that
model I wouldn't have done it so that's
what I mean so it's challenging that way
it's also challenging in that finally
you know Keaton IKEA is often bound up
with you know a kind of self
aggrandizement too and and there's
plenty of examples of individuals who do
this kind of thing in social media and
YouTube that becomes quickly very
inflationary for them and so so that's
that's why you might be sensing
some hesitation to me there's a part of
me that is I want to be and I hope I
have people help it I want to be aware
of the danger that I'm also confronting
and is this part of the way that you're
aware of it is by just what you're doing
right now you just kind of in a certain
sense you pause things for a moment said
okay just wanna yes yes
like posit and i flag it and I
acknowledge it I try to give it its due
I try to give it its due diligence so
that it has an active place in my
cognition and in my communication and
what's that what's the it's again it's
that we're giving due diligence to the
the the the the part of me that is
keeping a watch on the danger the part
of me that will alarm or signal a flag
saying be careful you know remember
remember so there's a pot so it's like
there's a there's an awareness of a
danger yes very much
we learn danger so you're just it
you're just making sure that that
awareness gets its due diligence yeah it
gets to speak it gets to speak because
it's it's you know again there's the
model of Socrates is divine sign he had
a thing is head I'm not claiming to have
that but he had something in his head
that would tell him when it would he was
about to do something wrong something
dangerous I tried to cultivate something
analogous to that for myself in this
process and involve other people in
helping to maintain it yeah because I
really like I do believe in what I'm
doing I think it's important and I want
to make keep that the focus of what I'm
doing yes and what I'm hearing actually
is what I'm hearing is actually where
some people that danger I can imagine
for some people because he said you said
you're so socially phobic the brain
atria so other people that warning would
be they have to constantly catch
themselves wanting to be famous or
wanting to to be that
be be the grand icing but I'm getting
this sense of that there's there's it
that one I got just to think about this
didn't imagine you as socially phobic or
to hear that that's true for you and
then here you are in fact right now
you're talking to somebody that has has
experienced you more like so much more
than you've experienced me because your
your work is out there so much that I'm
watching it and then I'm coming to you
and I have so I in a certain sense there
is a your name pops up and I'm drawn
towards it and that's not that it until
now has not been connected to you
personally engagement so there is this
element of where it's quite impressive
to imagine you as socially phobic and
what you're up to right now
well you know how you just described
that asymmetry of knowing I experienced
the of that part of me viscerally as a
vulnerability yeah that's like oh wait
that this is a huge asymmetry here and
that's a vulnerability but I mean yeah
so I acknowledge that I try not to let
it take over but that's definitely
that's definitely part of what's
happening very much so when you say
something like that it like there's a
part of me that goes oh right because I
feel like oh yes he knows he comes to me
with way more knowledge of me than I
possibly have a pyramid and so so right
there there's a quality of like where I
know that maybe somebody with a
different kind of personality profile or
a different temperament right may just
love that idea
like they pay for that idea right and
people have well however I I think the
thing that I'm appreciating is it then
actually there's a part of you that that
that's scary free yeah I mean there is a
part of me that likes the fame I'm not
I'm not trying to put that aside but
there's definitely a part of me and that
became very viscerally present
to me like like like in bad at night
that found it scary like you just said
found it very scary and continues to do
so not and not as bad as it was in the
first month or so of when the series
came and the first month or so the
series I almost stopped it because it
was just that sense of scariness was
just like Oh what have I done I've put
myself but again the the sense of being
on the track of the truth and and you
know being able to make a difference and
to help and the encouragement of other
people I kept going the encouragement
and your courage yeah that you're
demonstrating here it's just I have to
say I just feel I just feel a sense of
warmth and a certain kind of tenderness
[Music]
yeah just hearing that that's hearing in
a particular way how much you've risked
like this has really been a process of
you know your work out there has been
what I'm hearing is it fair to say that
there's a there is a symmetry with or
similarity between the process of you
being willing to be vulnerable in ways
that are deeply uncomfortable for you
and the work that you're feel called to
do in the world that you're doing in the
world that it's been
you better have a real relationship with
being vulnerable in there very much very
much and and I've met other people in
this process of this series where that
clearly clearly strikes me is how
they're coming to this so I get a sense
from you your willingness to be exposed
in the dialogue and so I I'm encouraged
by that and that that's something I look
for because it helps me if I if I don't
get locked into my own sense of
vulnerability and I can pick up on how
other people are taking the risk that
means a lot to me so I was walking home
and eclis had me on
is on his channel yeah and Paul Paul and
I I love Paul I have a lot of affection
for him a lot of respect for him some of
his commentary on my work is some of the
best commentary around but he's a he's a
committed Christian and I make a
distinction between a committed
Christian and a dogmatic Christian yes
he's a person and I used this
deliberately of good faith it I know
that in his and he I could he's saying
it and he's demonstrating it but he
still he is putting himself in a risky
position by talking to me because there
are many people in his audience who are
going to be like why are you talking to
this non-christian like what and and
some of the comments are exactly like
that and he he he's putting himself out
there he's putting himself at risk and I
sense and so I trust him more even
though and this is the thing this is the
thing that we've lost like I trust him
more even though in some ways I disagree
with him more than I disagree with other
people who I trust much less right does
that make sense it makes total sense it
makes total sense so what I'm hearing is
that there's a again I'm getting the
fractal sense this of that there's
there's it rather than the what someone
believes you're listening there's a
sense of a someone coming to being
together an openness that requires a
permeability and an openness to be
changed right which is always a risk
right and that's and that for you on
this path being kind of like having some
kind of like some social phobias who
said it's like you've had your own
process of feeling deeply exposed or at
risk yes all these asymmetries were or
now you have people in the world that
know more about you than you know about
them that you're then facing and talking
to yeah so you're like if it was just me
I don't know if I could do it it's
basically I heard you say it's like it
was just me and my thoughts laying a bed
at night in fact I almost I almost
called it off because it was just it was
just way too
tense yeah it was it was really bad but
when you look this is what makes sense
for them and see if I can kind of walk
walk through it it's like when you
encounter other people that are
demonstrating the same kind of courage
that that encourages you yes yeah that
there's some kind of strength I'm a wet
I'm imagining that when you go okay
they're doing that too yes um and I
would imagine it's less of a a result of
deductive reasoning it's more of a sense
of somebody is that it's much it's much
more of a skill than an argument that
runs through my head
it's but I I mean I I don't mean skilled
in a heavy-handed fashion I mean it like
a Taoist fitness yeah finesse of like
when you're when you're sparring it if
you've done Taichi it's like jazz moves
come out of you and you where did that
come from and those are the best moves
those are like and it's that there's
there's a skill but it's a finesse like
to use Pascal's idea it comes out and
yeah and so yeah when I'm talking to
Jonathan or I'm talking to Jordan Hall
or I'm talking to Paul van Utley and
they're coming from very different
worlds but nevertheless they're and
that's what I'm trying to I'm trying to
connote with this older meaning of good
faith not as the assertion of belief but
this commitment to connection right and
the and the courage to it in action yes
and that and that's what I see in these
guys and and like I say so that that
that's that that that's nurturing and
nutritious in some in very powerful way
I just felt I felt the new I felt a
nutrient again because that again it's
it feels like what we're talking about
is also the thing that I keep noticing I
feel yeah so what I mean that for me
when what you're talking about is also
what's happening in the talking that's
when you're getting into the
participatory knowing right yeah yeah so
I'm so so that's yes the participatory
knowing so there's been what one of the
things I've heard you say
often times you always made a point to
acknowledge the impact of other people
on your work and giving much that's very
important to me and I'm getting a deeper
sense of that right now like like
literally it's not just that you've only
had ideas that you didn't think of that
have influenced you
but I'm also hearing is it ask me if I'm
hearing this but like is that the people
that you're acknowledging you're also
acknowledging the way that you've been
you've received courage from them that's
been encouraging for you I hadn't made
that an explicit fought before but
that's exactly right that's exactly
right I'm trying to thank them not only
for the ideas we've made together but
you're right how as you know people like
Chris and Leo and Anderson mmm they well
they're they're like my brothers to me
they they they they keep me going in
ways or my wonderful partner she keeps
me going in in ways that again I can't
new on my own and yes you're right I
hadn't thought about that I want to I
want to think about that for a sec yep
applause and just like yeah just let
that happen because I feel I feel join
with you and this tenderness has just
opened up in appreciation yeah if there
is there's a lot um they've been there
for me I mean in yeah I'm thanking them
for that I mean some people I think and
I'm only thanking them for their work
because I only know them from their work
but you are right
there's people when I'm thanking them
I'm thanking them because they have
encouraged me in really really important
ways yeah that's really true I didn't
thought about that and thought about
that clearly like that that that is
really true that's very true and it it
means a lot to me
knowing that because I've I've been a
person who's often felt alone in some
ways and so that kind of connectedness
yeah that that's important I
[Music]
I heard you on actually Paul's interview
mm-hmm talk a little bit about the first
time I heard you talk about where some
of your backgrounds from yeah great
something something about like being it
growing up in what religious
fundamentalism yeah fundamentalist
Christian family extended family and no
of course when you're inside something
like that you don't understand it but it
was visceral I mean III would literally
be terrified as a child if I if I went
to somebody's house that wasn't a
Christian because I you know they would
there would be evil there and that was
or I remember coming home home one day
and there was nobody in the home and I
was convinced that the rapture hadn't
occurred and I had been left behind and
and and so I experienced this world
largely as terrifying and in a sense I
mean I have to be cautious when I talk
about Luther in the series because you
know there's that said that sense of
being rejected or always on the point of
being rejected by this very overbearing
sense of God and that and the way in
which that I saluted me which was quite
profound and it's it's funny because it
leaves it leaves the kind of mark on you
you have to be careful about because
because there's a part of you that longs
for that even when you know it's not
good for you and you have to yeah like
it's taken me time and I'm so in the
process the long term meaning longs for
the reject no no longs for that
encompassing world because even though
it's got that isolation in that
rejection it can it's this it's this
completely encompassing thing that you
are its Const within and
right and you have an important
narrative role in it right and so
there's like pulling that up like so you
can long for that right and and pulling
that apart from what I think it as what
we've been talking about this sense of
connectedness I I'm gonna talk about in
the series this this this sense that you
said aliveness the morning is an
alternative way of understanding
sacredness as something different from a
supernatural object that's permanently
sort of important and and stabili a
particular model of God that I think
well what I heard me personally was very
pernicious and punishing and so part of
what I've been trying to do it is to
separate that longing to go back all
right which I know is not healthy for me
from this other longing that we've been
exploring together here and and learning
to to not know because that's easy to
state conceptually but to sense the
sense the difference so that I can feel
the one pulling on me without feeling it
getting mixed up with the other pull on
me that's been very important right so
you just win it I want to make sure that
I'm I'm gonna make sure that I'm getting
it because it's it feels a couple of
things what you're saying
feels so alive to me on so many
different levels both levels of what I'm
understanding about you but also my own
understandings about what I've come to
and also my own experience as well and
in the whole conversation so I want to
make sure I just want to really
appreciate what you're saying so it's
like the that you come from there
there's a carefulness so a while back we
talked about a carefulness that's there
of of just allowing space for that which
has an eye on prey being basically right
size right like you need to make sure
cultivate humility right because one
you genuinely are right
you'll deeply deeply humble to by
multiple people
and so you cultivate that awareness
right and that there's also a danger
that comes with this experience of being
you could say famous yes right and in
that that's been a complicated
relationship for you really appreciating
the complexity of it because although
there is a part of you that once that
does want to be famous
Freyr there's also another part where it
is so it feels so exposing and
vulnerable such that finding other
people who have been willing to be
vulnerable in that way in a way that's
not self grand isin right yes yes has
been deeply encouraging for you very
much sir and and and so there's as we've
been talking about it then we started
bringing in to where you come from which
was what I'm hearing is and I think this
this distinction I want to just really
want to just because slow down and get
really kind of get this distinction
because it really it rumbled in me when
he said it that there's on one level you
described being in a you know in a in a
childhood that had a like was inside of
like a logical religious dogma yes world
in which there was this overbearing
presence that could reject you at any
moment yes right it's just that I just
cuz I don't come from well I in a
different way I do but that sense of
overbearing presence that could reject
you from any moment any moment and just
imagining that as being the in like
proactively encouraged way to structure
the world that just just that alone is
just impressive
I feel impressed by but then you said
something because Oh as you were saying
it i was thinking god that's really like
intensely awful then you said something
about like that you said another thing
that was really fascinating to me was
that yet I have to you said I have to be
careful because there's a struck the
structure of it of that world creates a
kind of holding and what I thought was
like almost like I thought of like a
wind cots holding environment yeah that
there that that because I come from
there that's the work that's one of my
origins or didn't press the Judas origin
I have to be careful too long for that
holding right that holding because what
comes with that holding is also a
personal narrative of my place in it yes
did I get it yep that's right
and I want to distinguish that from like
I said us this belonging to and
participating with other people in this
morning and keeping again not just
intellectually apart that's not that's
not enough they they have to be they
have to be they have to be to use bar
fields where there to be like a felt
change in consciousness of light so I
can sense the difference between them
because they for a very long time they
have been overlapped and confounded
together and a lot of the discernment
has been about trying to pull them apart
yes so what I'm hearing you say is like
one of the things that you've been doing
consciously in what's been emerging and
then becoming conscious in your work has
been this uniting of philosophy and
philosophy ax yeah what I'm hearing is
like you don't want to confuse is it
fair to say that I don't want to confuse
what holds right because if the
philosophy without the philosophy via
right is what holds that's like dogma
yes right yes
but if I say that what holds is actually
is the mutual fitted 'no said where i'm
open we were both open to being changed
by one another and novelty and one
another in such a way that that we that
deeply secures us at the same time it
allows us to become more and more open
that that that but that activity that
that relatedness is actually what is
worthy of relaxing into and being held
by yes okay got it
very much yeah well that was really
something just to kind of walk through
and read re say yeah I was yeah I was
it was reverberating in my chest yeah
very much you're just kind of letting
that reverberate for a moment like we'll
both be reverberating by it
what just like when you just look at
your like your life and what you've been
up to and your history and the people
that you're talking to and our
conversation what's it like just to have
all that reverberate right now
how does that's punch to you it's it's
wait it's it's joyful it's not pleasure
it's joyful I mean it's yeah it's that
there's a there's a sense of the deep
connectedness where you like where
you're in a place that you know where
you feel they connected to that
environment and and and you're
resonating and it's alive to you and
you're alive to it that's what I mean by
George that kind of thing mmm it's so
great that we're in that kind of thing I
feel you the thing that but what comes
to my mind almost always when when that
happens like it's coming to my mind
right now is like again I so many people
are hungry for this right and I would
very much
you know I think again you-you-you-you
I want to do more but I want to do more
and I keep trying anymore
I'm trying to help other people do more
yeah yeah and this more yeah this more
is I just feel more the present to doing
with you just right now
I so appreciate it well thank you very
much yeah absolutely I will I'll be
giving context for just for your work
and and links and stuff like that in the
beginning and after is there anything
that you would want to share just as we
complete our conversation and hopefully
just the first of many conversations I
would very much like to talk again yes
yeah well normally what I do at this
point is sort of you know I point people
to my series and also to the the
forthcoming one the one I'm working on
the after Socrates series which is in a
very real sense and I mean this word
strongly devoted to what we have been
talking about that's what this next
series is going to be centered on and so
if people found this helpful
I'm hoping that if they turn to that
next series they will also find it
helpful thank you thank you so much I
want to say I feel this conversate
experience we just had together was
really an experience very much yeah I
found it very moving and like really it
was a challenging for me at times
because I was trying to keep in the
conversation while also feeling I was
feeling very profoundly like emotionally
physiologically there was there was a
lot happening in me yes so this is like
- it's so interesting because this is
very much the essence of this for me is
is that what we've called circling
mm-hmm understood because for me
circling has been a a horizon in which
it keeps yielding to me right in a way
that's like to know it is to be
changed by in the process of knowing it
like yeah it feel that in very in ways
that I think I think I'll be listening
this conversation and a number of times
just to really understand the richness
that I currently feel even but to
distinguish it and really and really be
nourished by it even more so I
appreciate this a lot I really
appreciate it too I appreciate both for
the experience and I it has and this is
not to be in any way dismissive of other
interviews I've done in discussions this
was very very different and I felt I
felt that it gave me an opportunity to
exemplify much more what I want to
convey to people than just talking about
it and so I thank you for that
oh yes that's about the biggest thank
you that I could I could keep from you
thank you thank you thank you very much